{
  "reference_number": "10557",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Current goal of zero emissions by 2050 is aspirational but not realistic without a disastrous reduction in our living standards"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": "About 60% of our energy requirements are currently carbon based. We are feeding globally about 45 million people if the production\n is not here it will be produced elsewhere perhaps with greater consequence to the total GHG burden."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need an alternative scaleable energy source other than the combustion of fossil fuels. Nuclear energy must feature or the New\n\n Zealand economy will be at a competitive disadvantage to other countries with cheaper nuclear energy. Intermittent energy sources\n (solar wind and bio-fuels) are not concentrated are not readily scaleable and impose additional costs on reserve generation and grid\n\n stability."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Projections 30 years ahead are fraught with uncertainties. How about economic collapse due to high cost of energy."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Access to energy at competitive prices and an expanding economy are linked. At present the government does not have a plan that\n\n makes much sense. Proposed radical nuclear power reactor design promises electricity generation as cheap as coal fired\n generators."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We should start by increasing our competence in nuclear engineering and chemical engineering to transform our reliance on fossil\nfuels. Understand the relationship energy consumption per capita vs our ability maintain our society and infrastructure without\n\nexcessive debt."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need a long term plan beyond three year government terms. Define what the goals are besides zero carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The ETS is a construct that will not in itself solve the zero emissions but may incentivize certain policy directions. Of limited value."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I would have thought that part of the essential expertise would be the impact on business. Also if you need to transform our energy\neconomy you will need the expertise of both chemical and electrical engineering and the involvement of the private sector ho are at\n\nthe cutting edge of competing on the global markets."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It will dilute the focus of the bill. Should be a separate bill.."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Sounds overly bureaucratic. Let the local bodies deal with the risk management for example where people can build. The\n\nconsequences of climate change are by and large beyond our control."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is not a nuclear free moment in time. The energy density of nuclear s fossil fuel is about 5 orders of magnitude. The amount of\nenergy invested vs energy returned is hugely favourable. Even the Scandinavian countries who have abundant hydro and oil reserves\n(Norway) have a nuclear research program. The molten salt reactor will transform the the environmental footprint and economics of\n\nnuclear energy and New Zealand will be blind sided by this advance in nuclear technology. Moltex are scheduled to have their first\nmolten salt reactor licensed and operational by 2026."
    }
  ]
}
